Guide to the Louis Linden Madsen Papers 1956-1973
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Louis Linden Madsen Papers
1956-1973
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Cage 397
Madsen, Louis Linden
5 containers. 5 linear feet of shelf space. 1750 items.
Minutes, agendas, reports, resolutions, proposals, land and timber appraisals, correspondence and other papers relating to the monthly meetings of the Board of Natural Resources. Principal correspondents include Governors Albert Rosellini and Dan Evans, and Commissioner of Public Lands Bert Cole.
Louis Linden Madsen was born in Salt Lake City in 1907, received his Bachelor of Science Degree from Utah State Agricultural College in 1930, and went on to obtain his Doctorate from Cornell University in 1934. On July 1, 1955 he became the Director of the Washington State University Institute of Agricultural Science which, in 1965, was renamed the College of Agriculture. He retired from W.S.U. as Dean Emeritus in 1973. His papers, however, concern his tenure as a member of the Washington State Board of Natural Resources.
In 1957 the state of Washington enacted House Bill No. 68 which stipulated the creation of the Department of Natural Resources and its executive body, the Board of Natural Resources. This law also designated the board members as the Governor, the Superintendent of Public Instruction, the Commissioner of Public Lands, the Dean of the College of Forestry of the University of Washington, and the Dean or Director of the School of Agriculture of W.S.U. Dr. Madsen sat on the board from 1957 to 1973. The Board held its first meeting April 1, 1957 and, by law, chose the head of the Department of Natural Resources. The department, under the direction of the board, abolished and consolidated the functions of: the Board of State Land Commissioners; the Forestry Board; the Sustained-Yield Forest Committee; and others. The board itself exclusively controls and supervises the department and all public lands, including their use, lease, exchange, acquisition, sale, timber production, minerals, and other valuable materials.
The papers of Dr. Madsen are arranged in two series: the first, an alphabetized subject series; the second, a chronological correspondence series. The first series includes material from January 1957 to August 1967 and is mainly concerned with the forestry and agricultural interests of the Board of Natural Resources of which Dr. Madsen was a member. The second series includes material from November 1956 to March 1973 and is primarily a monthly correspondence file concerning the Board. Each of these files usually contains materials distributed to Board members for their monthly meetings: packets of proposed timber sales, Board proposals and resolutions, minutes and agendas, proposed land leases or exchanges, reports, correspondence, and other papers. The bulk of this series is from 1965 to 1973.
Principal correspondents include Governors Albert Rosellini and Dan Evans, as well as Commissioner of Public Lands Bert Cole.
This collection is open for research use.
The Dr. Louis Linden Madsen Papers were received by the Washington State University Libraries in February 1978 (UA 79-41) along with the records of the Department of Forestry and Range Management (UA 78-2).
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Madsen, Louis Linden, 1907- --Archives; Cole, Bert L.; Evans, Daniel J., 1925-; Rosellini, Albert D.
Washington (State). Board of Natural Resources; Washington (State). Governor (1957-1965: Rosellini); Washington (State). Governor (1965-1977: Evans)
Natural resources--Washington (State)--Management
Logging; Government and Politics
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Series 1: Subject File
  - Battelle: Log Export, November 30, 1964-March 1965; 9 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Blake Island, September 4, 1958-August 10, 1959; 22 items. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chermes Program, August 26, 1957-November 4, 1958; 9 items. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Colockum Creek Research Area, April 24, 1960- December 18, 1962; 55 items. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - European Pine Shoot Moth, June 10, 1960-June 6, 1962; 32 items. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Forest Roads, July-August 1967; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Forest Roads: Baker Report, May 3, 1960-March 14, 1961; 13 items. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fransen vs. Board, February 18, 1965-January 19, 1966; 15 items. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Harbor Line Commission, July 14, 1960-September 6, 1967; 15 items. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hemlock Looper, February 15, 1963-June 10, 1963; 12 items. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Legislative Bills: Department of Natural Resources, January 18, 1957-May 7, 1957; 13 items. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Publications: Department of Natural Resources, January 10, 1958-April 21, 1960; 10 items. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Red Lake Exchange, July 7, 1960-December 13, 1960; 24 items. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - University Grant Land Appraisals, February 24, 1965-March 9, 1965; 7 items. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Western States Land Commission Association, March 24, 1961-August 24, 1961; 16 items. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Yocolt Honor Camp, January 28, 1958-February 3, 1958; 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series 2: Chronological File
  - November 8, 1956-March 5, 1965, 125 items. (Box 1, Folder 17-26)
  - January 27, 1965-May 9, 1967, 415 items. (Box 2, Folder 27-56)
  - May 26, 1967-May 1, 1969, 305 items. (Box 3, Folder 57-78)
  - April 6, 1969-January 27, 1971, 340 items. (Box 4, Folder 79-108)
  - January 20, 1971-March 20, 1973, 315 items. (Box 5, Folder 109-133)